JOE: Different environments and
different situations can cause
individuals with sensory problems to
suffer sensory overload, and this has
to be considered when architects and
designers are creating spaces as they
need to factor this into their designs.
Small changes to an environment can
make changes to how an individual
with autism responds to stimuli.
However, all environments cannot be
made suitable for the sensory needs
of all individuals with autism.
BETH: There are things that can be done
in the home, schools and workplaces and
public buildings that can help, such as
changing the environment by addressing
any possible causes of over stimulation
which may cause sensory overload.
The most important thing is to be aware
of the sensory stimuli that the individual
responds to and how it affects them.
Sometimes preparing an individual
for some form of potential stimuli
can help them to be prepared.
JOE: In the home, making sure that
lights are not too bright and don’t
flicker, and sounds of electrical goods
are minimalised can relieve problems.
Sunglasses could help to combat
bright lights and blackout curtains
could help with sleeping and
hiding visual distractions from
view can improve a workspace.
An oversensitivity to sound can
be helped by shutting doors and
windows and eliminating unnecessary
sound such as mechanical noise.
The problem of everyday smells in the home
can be solved using low odour products.
Individuals who find textures or
patterns of clothing or soft furnishings
intolerable, can be helped by making sure
that patterns are kept to a minimum and
cushion covers, and other soft furnishings
and clothes have acceptable textures.
BETH: Each individual with autism
has their own sensory issues and if
these can be addressed and alleviated
to some extent, they can make a
world of difference to their lives.